today in our studio as we're
going to follow the lectures of the hour
we have several guests with us and some
of whom are young people
and I wonder if these
kids have ever heard their parents
give a particular answer to their
questions when you ask your dad dad why
can't I
go to the movie tonight or dad why can't
I drive the car
has your father ever said to you
in the answer
because you ever heard that yeah you bet
you have we've all heard it sometimes
you know I have my grandchildren and
they're bugging me with all kinds of
questions and I try to be patient and
explain them and sooner or later I run
out of patience and they say well why
can't we do that I just said just
because and I leave it at that but that
word seems such an innocent word
and yet it's a word that we use every
day in our normal conversation
what does it mean
when we say that something happens
because
we're assuming that there is a reason
that it happens
or more specifically that there is a
Cause
that brings it to pass
now in the history of philosophy
the person most famous for giving a
critical analysis of this whole idea of
cause
is the Scottish philosopher David Hume
Hume lived in the 18th century
he was born in 1711 died in
1776. I think many of you are familiar
with the significance of that date in
American history
but David Hume is considered by
theologians to be one of the most
formidable critics of Christianity
that the church has ever had to
encounter
and Hume wrote several books but the two
books that are most important
particularly for our concerns in this
course are his inquiry concerning human
understanding and his dialogues
concerning natural religion
because in the inquiry he gives a
comprehensive critique of causality and
in his dialogue he gives a comprehensive
critique of Miracles
nobody's name is more associated with a
repudiation of the idea of Miracle than
David Hume but again his major claim to
fame in the history of philosophy comes
as a result of his critical analysis of
the concept of cause or of causality
he was skeptical with respect to our
ability to know truth
because he realized that all empirical
knowledge
was based upon Sensations or impressions
and one of the questions he probed was
this
I opened my eyes and I see the world
around me
and I see all kinds of of of descriptive
things
in my eyes I see a group of people in
front of me here some that are very
young some that are not so very young
I'm not going to use the bad word there
and we have uh we have
a red shirt back here a green shirt up
here a teal shirt over here and so I
have a mass of colors and in the process
of all of this I am engaged in the act
of
individuation
individuation now maybe you've never
heard the term individuation but you've
certainly heard the term individual
when we say that some person is an
individual we mean simply that there's
one of them that you're not a split
personality that you're not two people
but you're one person you're a single
particular individual
now when we individuate things that
means that we have the ability even
though there's a group of people here I
recognize that that group is made up of
a plurality of individuals
and I look at an individual and I can
individuate certain parts of that person
the head the arms the Torso the legs the
feet and so on
now the Hume asked the question
how is it
that our senses are being bombarded
by all of these external stimulations or
Impressions how are we able
to sort this out
how can we pick out a particular
individual in the midst of a crowd why
don't all of these Sensations just get
all mixed up
in a chaotic blurb of sense impression
well he's saying that this is one of the
the great problems of philosophy is how
can this external Force give rise to
concrete
intelligible ideas
he also raised the question of how these
Sensations that we have these experience
of seeing tasting touching smelling and
so on how do they
relate to thoughts or ideas
and of the two that is ideas
and Sensations
which of those two is more lively
and Powerful
well for Hume
he would say the sensation
and these Sensations that give rise to
thoughts
we have the ability to remember
and he also probe the mystery of memory
which is something again that we take
for granted until we see somebody who
suffers from Alzheimer's or some
Advanced forms of hardening of the
arteries where they begin to lose their
capacity for memory
I deal with this all the time as a
teacher with my students where I give
them final exams at the end of the term
and
they don't always remember what they
were supposed to remember on the test in
fact just the other night for the church
in which I serve I serve on the
committee that examines candidates for
the ministry and I it's my job to
examine their Theology and they produce
papers where they give a summary of what
they believe and so on and I had this
young man before me the other night and
I read his doctrinal statement and I
circled five or six things on it that
gave me questions about the what this
fella believed and
and I began to interrogate him on a few
of these things and it was obvious to me
that he was a little bit confused about
some of these ideas
and finally I looked at him and I said
where did you learn your systematic
theology
who taught you Systematic Theology you
know what he said
I had you 15 years ago in this Seminary
and frankly I had forgotten that he was
ever one of my students and so now I
didn't know whether his uh lack of
precision on this particular element was
because the student didn't learn or
because the teacher didn't teach so I
had to help him along with it but
there's always the problem of memory he
did not keep in his mind the things that
I had taught him nor did I keep in my
mind
a good memory of him so we were both
having a problem with memory lapses
every single moment of every single day
you are being bombarded with Sensations
and Impressions you're seeing things
perhaps you've never seen before
and yet your mind has to record all of
that data I've said before you can make
a decision to this afternoon to stop
studying but you cannot make a decision
to stop learning
because as long as you're awake as long
as you're conscious as long as you're
conscious you're learning even if you
don't want to be learning you are
receiving information you're receiving
Sensations and data and that data is
being stored in your brain
but you don't remember it all do you I
have a hard time remembering what I did
yesterday
well one of the things one of the the
critical insights that Hume had
was how memory works and he said
that memory is inseparably related
to the original Sensations that you had
dependent upon their liveliness
or what he called their intensity
and their vivacity
now we have a little girl who's with us
today
who I believe is
11 years old 9 years old
nine years old and her name is Grace
is that right
did I get the age right Grace how old
are you
eight years old I could have sworn you
were nine you see how good my memory is
you told me just a few moments ago that
you were eight and already I have you a
year older than you were right Stephen
well
what happened there can you throw that
back to me because I can't work without
my Eraser
and I missed it
now
you know what I think
I think
Grace
that when you go back home to Alexandria
Virginia
you're not going to remember a whole lot
about what I'm teaching today about
David Hume
but you know what I bet you will
remember and you may even tell your
girlfriends when you get home said I
went to her this crazy Professor down in
Orlando and in the middle of his lecture
right there on TV he threw his eraser at
me do you think you'll remember that
you'll remember that if you don't
remember anything else because that
experience
would be more intense
and more Vivid
than the experience of listening to
abstract ideas
incidentally
Jonathan Edwards
who was preaching in the 18th century
and was the chief uh
spokesman for the Great Awakening in the
United States is famous for his sermons
as his most famous sermon of course is
sinners in the hands of an Angry God
and people you know are aghast when they
read that sermon when he talks about
Sinners being in such a precarious
situation that they're like a spider
hanging over this fire and they're just
being suspended by a single tiny sliver
of threat
and these Flames are beating and
thrashing about it and if Just One Flame
touches that little single spider web
thread what will happen to the spider
he'll fall into the fire and he's
telling the people of Northampton or or
of
where he gave that particular sermon
which wasn't North End he says
you were like that spider
you're hanging over the pit of Hell by a
slender threat with the Flames of divine
rash beating and thrashing about it
ready to burn it and send it in any
moment
and the only thing that keeps you from
falling into the fire is what
the hand of God
the grace of God
all right now people don't usually
preach like that today he also borrowed
some images from the Bible where he said
God's bow is bent
and his arrow is aimed at your heart
now that's Vivid isn't it
I mean you think about God as an Archer
with his bow bent and the and his arm is
quivering and you know that arrow is
going to come flying out of that string
any second
now
Jonathan edus wasn't just a preacher he
was a philosopher and he was acutely
aware of what was going on in Great
Britain in terms of this study of
Sensations
and he made it his practice to preach in
such a way as to use very graphic
concrete images
that would be Unforgettable images that
people would remember Sunday after
Sunday after Sunday
because he understood how the mind
actually works
well
in his analysis of all of these things
Hume then turned his attention
to the critical question of causality
because we do have an impression
of causality
the rain falls down and the grass gets
wet
why does the grass get wet
because it's raining see the grass gets
wet because it's raining what could be
more simple than that right well Hume
would look at that and say yes every
time I see the rainfall immediately
after the rain falls I find it the grass
is wet
and so I assume
that the reason why the grass is wet
is because the rain fell on it
and we said well of course that's what
you assume doesn't everybody assume that
and and human agree yes we all assume
that
but he said how do you know
that the reason why the grass is wet
is because it rained
how do you know that because one thing
follows another
that that which follows was caused by
the first thing
it's like asking the farmer what it is
that makes the sun rise every morning
and the farmer says oh I know what
causes the sun to come up every day and
he says what he says my rooster
he says because every morning my rooster
crows at the crack of dawn and as soon
as my rooster crowsed the sun comes up
now obviously he had a regular
experience of two things that happened
in sequence one thing that followed
after the other
and he made the Assumption right that
the second thing was caused by the first
thing and thereby committing one of the
oldest and most common logical fallacies
there happens to be and that's the
fallacy that's called the post-hoc
fallacy that says after this therefore
because of this
well we don't believe that the sun comes
up because the rooster crows
but there is
an ordinary
relationship
between the rain coming down
and the grass getting wet or we could
call that an ordinary connection
the question Hume was asking was is that
ordinary connection
a necessary connection
that is there an unyielding absolute
necessary connection between the rains
falling and the grass getting wet now
again here's where when you ask a
question like this some people rise up
in protest and say if that's what the
study of philosophy is about I'm getting
off of this bus because this is crazy I
mean obviously it's the rain that is
falling that is causing the grass to go
away well it wasn't obvious to the
occasional lifts of the 17th century
was it
it wasn't obvious
to leibniz with his theory of
pre-established Harmony
what these earlier thinkers had said
was
how do we know
that the real cause of the grass is
getting wet
is not the direct and immediate work of
God
makes it rain
and then his customary way of governing
his universe is he causes the grass to
get wet
every time after it rains but it's not
the rain that makes the grass wet it's
God that makes the grass wet do you
remember our struggle over the concepts
of primary and secondary causality
see
remember the occasional a smaller branch
for example who said
the grass is getting wet or the rain
falling is merely the occasion for God
to step into the gap and make the grass
wet
but can you see God stepping in
God's a spirit he's invisible so
how would we know whether it's a God
that's making the grass wet or the rain
that's making the grass wet
again that may seem like a silly
question at the beginning
but when we are concerned with the whole
broad scope of how this universe
operates
and we recognize what people were
beginning to understand in the 18th
century
that there's a whole lot more going on
out there than meets the eye
and how did we know that again through
the invention of the telescope
and we began to see things that were
happening
that without the telescope
we couldn't even imagine we're actually
going place going or taking place and so
what the skeptic is saying at this point
is who knows
what's really going on out there who
knows what is really causing one thing
to happen in a successive connection to
another now in his skepticism Hume
and we'll explore this more fully in our
next lesson but Hume said we have to
make a distinction
between
a customary
relationship
and a causal
and for Hume they are not necessarily
the same thing that's what I've been
trying to explain for the last few
minutes
it is a custom of our experience to see
grass getting wet after it rains
we therefore assume
that there is a necessary connection
between the rains falling and the grass
is getting wet
but those are not the same thing
and so what Hume is going to do is
explain to us the mystery of causal
relationships from a different
perspective that raises questions about
the reality of causality itself
now what's the significance of that
particularly for Christianity
when I say why do you believe in Jesus
you may say to me because God raised him
from the dead
do we know that God caused it anybody
witness God's action there
no
in fact that raises the question of
Miracles can we believe Miracles at all
why do you believe that there is a God
and you say well I look at the world
around me somebody had to cause it
much of the arguments for the existence
of God historically have been based on
reasoning
from the need for a cause and not just
for the argument for the existence of
God but to remember Descartes famous
formula I think therefore I am and I
asked the question at that time what was
Descartes assuming when he says I think
therefore I am
he was assuming that if he's thinking
if if he is doubting
there must be a cause of that doubt
there must be a doubter
and for there to be a doubter there must
be a cause of there being a doubter
there must be a thinker
and for there to have to have thought
there has to be a thinker and for a
thinker to be for a thinker to think he
has to be
he's assuming
causality all the way through that
argument well causality is an assumption
that every philosopher ever lived has
has used
and now for the first time it's coming
under rigorous attack by David hume's
analysis which raises serious problems
for biblical Christianity and
for science